# Ramakrishnan Sundara Raman

### PhD Candidate, University of Michigan

☐ ramaks@umich.edu

https://ramakrishnansr.com/

in ramakrishnansundararaman

I am a PhD candidate with 6+ years of experience in computer security and networking research, with expertise in building empirical methods to detect, analyze and prevent large-scale threats to Internet users' security and privacy. My research involves longitudinally measuring Internet censorship and connection tampering at global scale, and examining the technologies that enable tampering. I lead work on the Censored Planet Observatory, and I am the recipient of a FOCI Rising Star Award, an OTF Information Controls Fellowship, and an IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize.

# **Education**

2018 - Present

PhD Candidate, University of Michigan in Computer Science and Engineering

**Advisor:** Prof. Roya Ensafi

Thesis title: Global, Longitudinal, and Data-Driven Investigation of Network Restrictions

CGPA: 3.95 out of 4

2013 - 2017

■ Bachelor of Technology, Vellore Institute of Technology in Computer Science and Engineering

Project Title: Measuring Last-Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather

**CGPA**: 9.69 out of 10 Rank in CSE: 2 out of 648

## Conference Publications

Modeling and Detecting Internet Censorship Events

E. Tsai, R. Sundara Raman, A. Prakash, R. Ensafi

Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2024

Global, Passive Detection of Connection Tampering

R. Sundara Raman, L.H. Merino, K. Bock, M. Fayed, D. Levin, N. Sullivan, L. Valenta

ACM SIGCOMM, September 2023

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/passive.pdf

Network Responses to Russia's Invasion of Ukraine in 2022: A Cautionary Tale for Internet Freedom

R. Ramesh\*, R. Sundara Raman\*, A. Virkud, A. Dirksen, A. Huremagic, D. Fifield, D. Rodenburg, R. Hynes, D. Madory, R. Ensafi

USENIX Security Symposium, August 2023

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/russia-ukraine-invasion.pdf

Detecting DNS Manipulation using TLS Certificates

E. Tsai, D. Kumar, R. Sundara Raman, G. Li, Y. Eiger, R. Ensafi

Privacy Enhancing Technologies Symposium (PETS), July 2023

♠ https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/certainty.pdf

Network Measurement Methods for Locating and Examining Censorship Devices

R. Sundara Raman\*, M. Wang\*, J.Dalek, J. Mayer, and R. Ensafi

ACM Conference on emerging Networking EXperiments and Technologies (CoNEXT), December 2022

TRTF Applied Networking Research Prize

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/censorship\_devices.pdf

A Large-scale Investigation into Geodifferences in Mobile Apps

R. Kumar, A. Virkud, R. Sundara Raman, A. Prakash, and R. Ensafi

USENIX Security Symposium, August 2022

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/appmap.pdf

Lost in Transmission: Investigating Filtering of COVID-19 Websites

A. Vyas, R. Sundara Raman, N. Ceccio, P. Lutscher, and R. Ensafi

Financial Cryptography and Data Security (FC), March 2021

♦ https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/covid.pdf

Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory

R. Sundara Raman, P. Shenoy, K. Kohls, and R. Ensafi

ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), November 2020

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/censoredplanet.pdf

### O Investigating Large Scale HTTPS Interception in Kazakhstan

**R. Sundara Raman**, L. Evdokimov, E. Wustrow, A. Halderman, and R. Ensafi ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), October 2020

P Best Paper Award Nominee

₱ https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/Kazakhstan.pdf

### O Measuring the Deployment of Network Censorship Filters at Global Scale

R. Sundara Raman, A. Stoll, J. Dalek, R. Ramesh, W. Scott, R. Ensafi

Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2020

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/filtermap.pdf

### O Decentralized Control: A Case Study of Russia

R. Ramesh, R. Sundara Raman, M. Bernhard, V. Ongkowijaya, L. Evdokimov, A. Edmundson, S. Sprecher, M. Ikram, R. Ensafi

Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2020

Top 10 Paper CSAW'20 Applied Research Competition North America Top 10 Paper

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/russia.pdf

# **Workshop Publications**

### Advancing the Art of Censorship Data Analysis

R. Sundara Raman, A. Virkud, S. Laplante, V. Fortuna, R. Ensafi

Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), February 2023

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/censorship-data-analysis.pdf

### A Multi-Perspective View of Internet Censorship in Myanmar

R. Padmanabhan, A. Filastò, M. Xynou, **R. Sundara Raman**, K. Middleton, M. Zhang, D. Madory, M. Roberts, and A. Dainotti

Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), August 2021

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/myanmar.pdf

### **Awards**

### Research FOCI'23 Rising Star Award

July 2023

₱ https://ramakrishnansr.com/images/foci-rising-star.jpeg

#### ■ IRTF Applied Networking Research Prize (ANRP) 2023

January 2023

♦ https://www.ietf.org/blog/anrp-2023/

### **■ HotPETs 2022 Best Talk Award**

July 2022

♦ https://petsymposium.org/best-hotpets-talks.php

# ■ University of Michigan CSE Graduate Student Honors Runners Up Award

November 2020

₱ https://cse.engin.umich.edu/stories/2020-cse-graduate-student-honors-competition-highlights-outstanding-research

### ACM IMC 2020 Best Paper Award Nominee

October 2020

### **Fellowships**

### Rackham Predoctoral Fellowship

March 2023

♦ https://cse.engin.umich.edu/stories/ram-sundara-raman-earns-rackham-predoctoral-fellowship

#### OTF Information Controls Fellowship (ICFP) Award

November 2021

Teaching & Service

### North Campus Deans' MLK Spirit Award 2023

January 2023

♦ https://culture.engin.umich.edu/2023-nominees-recipients/

### ■ University of Michigan CSE GSI Honorable Mention Award

August 2021

♦ https://ramakrishnansr.com/images/honorable\_mention\_award.pdf

Grants

#### ACM IMC 2022 Travel Grant

October 2022

#### DARPA MICE Grant

Title: Leveraging machine learning to build an intelligent Censored Planet observatory August 2021

### ■ USENIX Security 2020 Student Grant

August 2020

### ■ Citizen Lab Summer Institute (CLSI) 2019 Travel Grant

August 2019

# **Teaching**

Topic: Censorship and Circumvention

January 2023 – April 2023 📕 Substitute Instru

■ Substitute Instructor, EECS 588, University of Michigan

Topic: Computer and Network Security

Topic: Censorship and Circumvention

August 2020 – December 2020

Graduate Student Instructor (GSI), EECS 588, University of Michigan

Topic: Computer and Network Security

GSI Honorable Mention Award

# **Work Experience**

July 2022 – September 2022

### Research Intern, Cloudflare Inc.

- Designed a large network monitoring system that identifies anomalous network events such as connection tampering attacks in large-scale network traffic at the rate of millions of packets per second.
- Developed network data analysis methods and tools for detecting large-scale traffic tampering passively from an operator's point of view.
- Built production dashboards and reports showcasing significant network events such as the effects of the protests in Iran on Internet traffic.

November 2021 – July 2022

### OTF Senior ICFP Fellow in Information Controls, The Citizen Lab

- Researched novel measurement methods for locating and examining network devices that performed surveillance and censorship.
- Collaborated with the expert team at the Citizen Lab, a research group focused on network forensics.
- Published several open-source tools and fingerprint datasets for identifying censorship devices.

July 2017 – May 2018

### Associate Consultant, Microsoft Global Delivery

Contributed to large enterprise systems for business applications that can deliver value to large organizations around the world.

March 2017 - July 2017

#### Research Intern, University of Maryland

Advisor: Prof. Neil Spring

- Facilitated a measurement platform and analysis tools that identifies last-mile residential Internet outages in areas affected by severe weather conditions in real-time.
- Poster presented at ACM Internet Measurement Conference 2017: "Measuring Last-Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather"

May 2016 – July 2016

Intern, Microsoft Global Delivery

Integrated data analytics into Microsoft's project management tool, built on ASP.NET. Microsoft's Power BI tool was utilized to make interactive reports that provided valuable insight to the users.

# Mentoring

- Undergraduate Students: Nadav Oren (2023), Apurva Virkud (2020 2022), Anjali Vyas (2020 2021), Rose Ceccio (2020 2021), Prerana Shenoy (2019 2020)
- O Graduate Students: Kevin Wang (2023), Elisa Tsai (2020 2023)

## **Talks**

O Conference Talk: Global, Passive Detection of Connection Tampering

ACM SIGCOMM, September 2023

• https://youtu.be/RD73IgzQMFo?si=OWvNnlNNLalbhygV&t=2984

 Conference Talk: Network Responses to Russia's Invasion of Ukraine in 2022: A Cautionary Tale for Internet Freedom

Usenix Security Symposium, August 2023

Workshop Talk: Advancing the Art of Censorship Data Analysis
 Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI), February 2023

- Lightning Talk: Exploring Internet censorship through the Censored Planet Dashboard
   Open Technology Fund (OTF), January 2023
- Conference Talk: Network Measurement Methods for Locating and Examining Network Censorship Devices
   Conference on emerging Networking Experiments and Technologies (CoNEXT 2022), December 2022
- Workshop Talk: Improving Usability of Internet Censorship Data through a Censorship Dashboard
   15th Workshop on Hot Topics in Privacy Enhancing Technologies (HotPETs), July 2022
   Best Talk Award
- \_

 Tech Demo: Exploring Internet censorship with the Censored Planet Dashboard RightsCon 2022, June 2022

₱ https://youtu.be/j1sLWAmOnMA

Symposium Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory
 The 5th Annual Data for Public Good Symposium, March 2022

♦ https://midas.umich.edu/2022-d4pg/research-talks/#research-talks

Invited Talk: Censored Planet Community Webinar 2021

Censored Planet, October 2021

• https://youtu.be/v5G\_nUUzVv8

 Invited Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide Longitudinal Observatory NDSS DNS Privacy Workshop (DNSPriv), February 2021

O Conference Talk: Censored Planet: An Internet-wide Longitudinal Observatory ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS), November 2020 

https://youtu.be/8dwZdNkJ508

 Conference Talk: Investigating Large Scale HTTPS Interception in Kazakhstan ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), October 2020

f https://youtu.be/RoYWsfNOCr4

O Invited Talk: Censored Planet: Measuring Internet censorship remotely

OONI Internet Measurement Village (IMV), June 2020

♦ https://youtu.be/5IgnvR42cMQ

 Conference Talk: Measuring the Deployment of Network Censorship Filters at Global Scale Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS), February 2020

# Reports and Blogposts

### Measuring Connection Tampering Around the World

Internet Society Pulse Blog, October 2023

## https://pulse.internetsociety.org/blog/measuring-connection-tampering-around-the-world

### Making Censorship Data More User Friendly

Internet Society Pulse Blog, May 2023

## https://pulse.internetsociety.org/blog/making-censorship-data-more-user-friendly

### Profiling Internet Censors: Methods to Measure and Locate Censorship Devices

Open Technology Fund (OTF), December 2022

• https://www.opentech.fund/news/profiling-internet-censors-methods-to-measure-and-locate-censorship-devices/

### An analysis of a large-scale HTTPS interception

APNIC Blog, February 2021

## https://blog.apnic.net/2021/02/15/an-analysis-of-a-large-scale-https-interception/

### O US Government and military websites are geoblocked from Hong Kong and China

Censored Planet, August 2020

• https://censoredplanet.org/hongkong

### **Posters**

- Censored Planet: An Internet-wide, Longitudinal Censorship Observatory Midwest Security Workshop, April 2019
- Measuring Last Mile Internet Reliability During Severe Weather ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC), November 2017

# **Certifications**

### O 2023 Rackham-CRLT Preparing Future Faculty Seminar

University of Michigan, June 2023

• https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/pff2023.pdf

### Introduction to Data Science in Python

University of Michigan Coursera, June 2023

₱ https://ramakrishnansr.com/assets/coursera-intro-data-science-python.pdf

### Service

Chairing

Session Chair at FOCI'21

₱ https://conferences.sigcomm.org/sigcomm/2021/workshop-foci.html

Reviewing

■ TPC Member, IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2024

https://sp2024.ieee-security.org/cfpapers.html

TPC Member, Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI) 2024

₱ https://foci.community/foci24.html

- Reviewer, 6th International Conference on Computer Science and Application Engineering (CSAE) 2022
- ▼ TPC Member, ACM SIGCOMM 2021 Workshop on Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI)

₱ https://conferences.sigcomm.org/sigcomm/2021/workshop-foci.html

### External Reviewing

- **USENIX Security Symposium 2022**
- ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC) 2021
- USENIX Security Symposium 2021
- ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC) 2020
- IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2020

- Privacy Enhancing Technology Symposium (PETS) 2020
- USENIX Security Symposium 2019
- IEEE Symposium on Security and Privacy (S&P) 2019

### Leadership

# Outreach Chair at CSEG, UM CSE graduate student organization June 2020 – May 2022

My responsibilities included arranging and managing outreach events throughout the year that aimed at spreading knowledge about computer science research in various schools, colleges and groups. I also participated as the DEI committee student representative of CSEG in early 2022.

T Deans' MLK Spirit Award 2023

# Administrator of the Security Reading Group (SECRIT) in UM CSE

June 2019 – June 2021